Why am I me?
（フシ）
なんでオレはオレなんだろう
I couldn't...
何も… 何もできなかった
I couldn't do anything.
Gugu...
グーグー ごめんなさい
I'm sorry.
It's too late.
もう遅い
（雷鳴）
♪～
～♪
It's been four and a half days
since Fushi left Booze Man's home.
（観察者）
酒爺(さけじい)の家を出て４日と半日
Fushi walked alone, in silence.
フシは１人 黙々と歩いていた
Along the way, he tried on many expressions.
道すがら
フシは いろいろな表情をした
He must be desperately trying
to process his emotions.
内に秘めた思いを処理しようと
必死なのだろう
With Gugu's death, he seems to have
acquired something invisible.
グーグーの死を経て
目に見えないものも獲得したようだ
Come out, black thing.
おい 出てこい 黒いの
By "black thing," do you mean me?
（観察者）
“黒いの”とは私のことか？
What is it?
何だ？
This is the first time you've called for me.
呼び出されるのは初めてである
Aspiring to Go Higher
What am I supposed to do now?
オレは これから
どうすればいい？
Continue forward.
（観察者）そのまま進み
Become stronger so that you can take
back the piece that was taken from you.
奪われた お前の一部を
取り戻すために強くなりなさい
What... What am I?
オレは… オレは一体 何だ？
What do you want from me?
お前はオレをどうしたいんだ？
It's as I've said before.
（観察者）以前 話したとおりだ
You are a mechanism for collecting and
preserving the information of this land.
お前は この地の情報を収集し
保存するための装置だ
And it was I who created you.
それを作ったのが この私だ
I am effectively your parent.
私は いわば
お前の親のようなものだ
No. You aren't my parent.
違う お前は親なんかじゃない
My parent was...
オレにとっての親は…
Is something the matter?
（観察者）どうかしたか？
Why am I the only one living?
（フシ）なんでオレだけ生きて…
Why did Gugu have to d-d-die?
グーグーが死ななきゃ
いけなかったんだ？
It's simply a difference in nature.
（観察者）ただの性質の違いだ
I have no idea what you're talking about.
（フシ）意味が分からない
It's too early for you to understand.
（観察者）
それを知るには まだ早い
But I'm glad you're able to question things.
しかし お前が疑問を持てるように
なったことが うれしい…
Don't play dumb with me.
ごまかすな 全部話せ
Tell me everything!
Everything perishes.
（観察者）すべてのものは滅びる
That's why you're needed.
だから お前が必要なのだ
You're the one special entity in this world.
お前は この世で唯一
特別な存在だ
For that reason, the enemies,
the Nokkers, seem to want to control you.
敵… ノッカーは
そんな お前を支配したいようだ
Will the Nokkers stop coming if I'm not me?
ノッカーは… オレが
オレでなくなったら来ないのか？
That would be nice.
（観察者）だったらいいがな
I'll try it.
試してやる
（フシ）うわっ
くっ
Taking on that form doesn't constitute
having abandoned yourself.
（観察者）そうなることは
お前を放棄したことにならない
If the Nokkers come while you're in that form,
they'll simply have their way with you.
この間にノッカーが来れば
好きなようにされるだけだ
If you continue to lose, you'll return to
a state of nothing—back to the orb.
もし やられ続けたら
お前はゼロの状態…
つまり球(きゅう)に戻る
And you'll never return to what you are now.
そうなれば二度と
今のお前には戻らない
You won't be able to.
いや 戻れない
I wouldn't mind, but I'm sure you would.
私は困らないが お前は困るだろう
Why don't you fight, then?
そこまで言うなら お前が戦えよ！
You're strong enough to
control me, aren't you?
お前はオレをシハイできる
くらいには強いんだろ？
Yes. It would indeed be simple.
（観察者）ああ 確かに たやすい
But even if I can control your body,
I can't control your mind.
しかし肉体は支配できても
精神は支配できない
The Nokkers...
ノッカー
Until their objective of killing us is put
to an end, the attacks will continue.
ヤツらの“私たちを討つ”という
目的を破壊せぬかぎり
攻撃は続く
It will be you, not me, who stops them.
それを止めるのは
私ではなく お前だ
One day, I will no longer be here.
私は いずれ いなくなる
You need to prepare to defeat them
on your own when that time comes.
そのときに向けて
お前は１人で打ち勝てるように
なっておく必要がある
You're a critical step in achieving my goal.
私の目的を達成するための
大事な足がかりとして…
That's your problem!
勝手だ！　そんなの知らない！
I don't care!
あ… ううっ！
Good grief.
（観察者）やれやれ…
手のかかるものに育ってしまった
You've grown to be quite troublesome.
Damn it.
（フシ）クソッ
Nothing will bring Gugu back.
ナニやっても
グーグーは かえってこない
So I don't care anymore.
ダカラ モウ どうでもいい
I don't care what happens
to me or anyone else.
ナニが おきようが
オレが どうナロウガ…
Are you sure about that?
（観察者）
本当に そう言い切れるかな？
（風が吹く音）
This scent... Why?
（フシ）このニオイ… なんで？
（ピオラン）ひゃっ
Pioran!
（フシ）ピオラン？
（ピオラン）よう！
Hey!
I realized something.
（ピオラン）わしは気づいたんじゃ
I came to Takunaha hoping I could help you,
お前を助けてやれるかもと思って
タクナハへ来たが
but in the end, I couldn't
do anything for you,
結局 何もしてやれんかったって
ことにな
so I decided to travel with you again.
だから また お前に
ついていくことにした
B-But...
ソ… ソンな…
Wh-What about the old man and the others?
じ… じいたちは どうナルの？
Don't worry.
（ピオラン）安心しろ
わしの考えは ちゃんと伝えておる
I've told them all about what I'm doing.
Rean and Shin said they'd keep
the business going for us.
リーンやシンも あの店を
支えてくれると言っておった
Rean had figured out what
happened to you and Gugu.
リーンはな お前やグーグーのこと
悟っておったぞ
I think that's why she let me leave.
だからこそ わしを送り出して
くれたんじゃと思う
Pioran...
（フシ）ピオラン
Go home.
帰って
How dare you?!
ほえ？　なんと！
You're turning down an
innocent old lady's wish?
いたいけなババアの申し出を
断るのか？
You know what follows me.
オレの所にはアレが来る 危険だ
It's dangerous.
I've thought it through.
わしは考えた
How do I give meaning to what little
time I have left in this life?
老い先短い人生に
どう意味を持たせるかと
I'll be your walking stick.
ならば一寸でもいい
Even if I'm just an inch-long twig.
お前を支える棒きれになろう
That's what I want to do.
そう思ったんじゃ
I'm dragging you home!
（フシ）家まで連れてく
（ピオラン）あ～ ヤじゃ！
They need you at that home, Pioran!
あの家にはピオランが必要なんだ！
Ow!
イタッ
（２人の荒い息）
Why won't you listen to me?
なんで言うこと
聞いてくれないんだ！
I don't want anyone to cry anymore.
オレは もう誰かが泣くのは
イヤだし
A-And I don't want to see it, either.
それを見るのもイヤなんだ
So please, go home!
だから帰ってよ！
オレのために帰って！
Go home for my sake!
Shut up!
うるさい わしの人生じゃ！
It's my life!
（フシ）うっ イタッ
痛いよ…
Let me do as I please!
わしの好き勝手させろ！
ハァ ハァ ハァ…
Suit yourself.
（フシ）勝手にしろ
Here, have a potato.
（ピオラン）ほれ イモ
Don't want it.
いらない
Here, have some tea.
（ピオラン）ほれ 茶
Don't want it.
いらない
Here, have some fish.
（ピオラン）ほれ 魚
I said I don't want it!
いらないって！
You must be cold.
寒かろうに…
Pioran, promise me one thing.
（フシ）ピオラン １つ約束して
What's that?
何じゃ？
Don't die.
死なないで
うむ
Look.
（ピオラン）おい 見ろ 街じゃ
It's a town.
I'm starving.
腹も減ったし ここいらで
いっちょ休憩しようぞ
It's a good time for a break!
でやっ
Pioran!
ピオラン？
（麵をすする音）
Pioran, let's go already.
ピオラン 早く出よう
Welcome!
（店主）らっしゃい！
I haven't eaten in ages! Delicious!
か～ 久々の麺じゃ ウマいの！
I can't protect this village if it comes back.
もしも あいつが来たとき
オレじゃ この街を守れない
Fine. Just give me a second.
わあった ちょっとだけな
Hey, man! Do you have booze?
にいさん 酒あるか？
Sure thing.
Pioran!
（店主）あいよ！
ピオラン！
Hey, where are the Nokkers right now?
おい ノッカーは今
どこにいるんだ？
Six kilometers northwest of here.
（観察者）ここから６キロ北西だ
I haven't sensed it move for the past four
days, since it burrowed into the soil.
この４日間 地中に潜ったまま
動きは感じられない
Sensed?
感じる？
You always know where they are?
いつでも敵の位置が分かるのか？
They're like insects crawling on your body.
（観察者）
体を這(は)う虫みたいなものだ
You wouldn't notice them
while they're small eggs,
小さい卵の状態では気づかぬが
but once they hatch and start to move,
they cause intense discomfort.
孵化(ふか)して動きだすと
ひどい不快感がする
Can't you explain in a way I can understand?
ん？　もうちょっと
分かるように言ってくれよ
Who are you talking to?
（ピオラン）
誰と しゃべっとるんじゃ？
Oh, well...
あ… その…
Here's your food.
ん？
（ピオラン）ほれ お前のメシじゃ
Fushi.
フシ
（フシ）ああ…
You can tell me anything.
何でも言え
A man in black?
（ピオラン）黒い男か…
And he's telling you to become stronger?
そいつが お前に
強くなれと言うんじゃな
To drive away the Nokkers?
ノッカーを追い返すために
Yeah.
（フシ）うん
So, what do you want to do?
で お前は どうしたいんじゃ？
Huh?
え？
I don't want to just do as he says.
（フシ）
あいつの言いなりになるのはイヤだ
But if the Nokkers come...
でも もしノッカーが
襲ってきたら…
I would be the only one
who could protect Pioran.
そのとき
ピオランを守れるのはオレだけ
The man in black is right.
I can't defeat them.
黒いのが言うように
オレじゃ勝てない
Not as I am now.
今のオレじゃ…
Then I have to become strong.
だったら強くなるしか…
あっ
That bastard!
He made me bump into Pioran
knowing this would happen to me!
（フシ）あいつ！　オレが
こうなるのを分かってて
わざとピオランに会わせたな
Say, Fushi...
のお フシよ
I don't expect you to protect me.
わしは
お前に守ってくれとは思わん
え？
Living on the edge has its appeal, too.
浮き草のように生きるのも
ええもんじゃぞ…
You hear?
のう？
Yeah.
うん
Is that really good enough?
（フシ）本当に それでいいのか？
I feel like I'm forgetting something.
何か忘れてる気がする
Those fruits look delicious!
（ピオラン）
おう ウマそうな果物じゃ
Fushi, climb up and grab them for me.
フシよ
ちょっと登って取ってくれ
I don't have to do that.
そんなことしなくても… ほら
See?
Gross!
うえっ きしょい！
I'm not eating that.
そんなもん よう食べんわ
Oh, fine.
（フシ）ふん… 仕方ないな…
Huh?
あれ？　うっ
What's wrong? That was pathetic.
（ピオラン）何じゃ 情けない
Just take on March's form again.
How hard could it be?
前みたいにマーチの姿でやれば
簡単じゃろうよ
March?
マーチ？
M-March! You know her, don't you?
お前… マーチじゃ
知っとるじゃろ あのちっこいの
The tiny one.
Who are you talking about?
誰のこと？
You've changed into her tons of times!
何度も あの娘に
なり変わったじゃろ
Remember her!
思い出せ！
忘れたとは言わせんぞ！
Don't you dare tell me you've forgotten her!
（ピオラン）うっ
I remember.
覚えてるよ ちゃんと
木に登れた記憶はある
I remember being able to climb trees.
Fushi! You go first!
（グーグー）フシ 先に行け！
Fushi! Give me a stick!
フシ 棒をくれ！
I do...
確かに…
You were robbed.
（観察者）お前は奪われたのだ
ノッカーにマーチを
The Nokkers took March from you.
Someone gave me many things.
（フシ）たくさんのものを
オレにくれた人がいた
Say "thank you."
（マーチ）
ほら “ありがとう”って
Funny puppy!
ヘンなワンちゃん！
Growing up means knowing everything, right?
大人になるって
知っていくってことでしょ？
Is that...
あれが…
あれがマーチなのか？
Is that March?
Wasn't she really important to me?
（フシ）ものすごく
大事なものだったんじゃ…
You finally understand.
（観察者）ようやく気づいたか
I can't blame you.
仕方ない 失ったものは
思い出すことすらできない
You can't even recall something
once you've lost it.
I see.
（ピオラン）なるほど
The enemy takes your memories, too.
敵は お前の記憶も奪うのか
If it killed you while
you were in Gugu's form,
もしグーグーの姿の
お前がやられたら
you'd lose your memories of Gugu, too.
グーグーの記憶も
なくすんじゃな
Yeah.
うん
It's like a second death.
まるで２度目の死じゃな
え？
Rean and Booze Man, Parona of Ninannah...
（ピオラン）リーンや酒爺
ニナンナのパロナ
そして わしも…
And me, too.
We'll only be truly dead
once we're forgotten.
忘れられて初めて
本当の意味で
死んでいくんじゃろうな
I won't let that happen.
そうはさせない
オレ 強くなる
I'll get stronger.
Now that I've made up my
mind, I have to think.
（フシ）決めたからには
考えなければ
Even if I'm playing right
into the black thing's hands.
たとえ黒いのの
狙いどおりだとしても
You make new things in
reaction to pain, right?
（グーグー）お前は痛みに反応して
新しいものを作るんだよな
Pain...
（フシ）痛み…
シゲキを与えればいい
I just have to stimulate myself.
It's easy.
簡単だ
But I can't turn myself into rock.
でも自分を石にするのはダメだ
I'll lose awareness.
イシキがなくなる
The problem is that,
as far as living things go,
問題は生き物のとき
I can't transform while the
subject is still alive.
相手が生きてるうちは
変身できない
What a nasty thought.
A crab flower!
ヤな感じだ
（ピオラン）
おう カニフラワーか
These things are sweet.
こいつはウマいぞ
The eyes are made of bugs,
so we don't eat them.
（ピオラン）
目は虫でできてるから食べん
The flower is delicious,
so we'll make salad out of it later.
フラワーの部分は おいしいから
あとでサラダにする
And we boil it live with plenty of salt.
生きたまま多めの塩でゆでる
What's wrong, Fushi?
（フシ）ん…
（ピオラン）どうした フシ？
When I'm near something, I feel what it feels.
近くにいると伝わってくるんだ
Pain and suffering and stuff.
痛みとか イヤな感じとか…
Wow.
なんと！
今までずっと そうだったのか？
Has it always been like that?
Yeah.
うん
That's why I always had Gugu
gut the fish and crabs.
だから魚やザリガニを
さばくときは
全部グーグーに やってもらってた
I never knew.
そうか
There, it's ready.
（ピオラン）ほれ できたぞ
Yum!
Yeah, it's good.
（ピオラン）ウマい！
（フシ）うん ウマい
I don't have the guts to become a crab yet.
（フシ）
まだカニになる度胸はないな
All I can make is a corpse.
作れるのはシガイか
I guess I could probably make Gugu, too.
きっとグーグーも作れるんだな
A limp, motionless Gugu.
グッタリして動かないグーグーが…
Say, Fushi...
（ピオラン）のう フシよ
How did you defeat the Nokkers
when you fought them last time?
お前が前に
ノッカーと戦ったときは
どうやって勝った？
え？　ああ…
それが よく分からないんだ
I actually don't know.
Gugu blew fire on it,
and it jumped in the water,
グーグーの火でガーってやって
水の中に入ったら
and the rocks on its body fell apart.
体の岩が砕けて…
That's it!
それじゃ！
Heated stone becomes brittle
when it's quickly cooled.
熱した石は
急に冷やすと もろくなる
あ！
That did work well.
確かに あのときは
うまくいったけど
But I don't know about the next time.
次は どうなるか…
If it shakes me off, I'll die.
振り落とされたら死んでしまう
And you can't count on
there being water nearby.
そう都合よく水があるとは限らんし
You're going to have to learn
to be versatile when you fight.
臨機応変に戦えるようにならんとな
I know!
そうじゃ！
いい場所があるぞ フシ
There's a place that's perfect, Fushi!
There's a ship that goes to
Sarlnine from the port up ahead.
（ピオラン）この先の港から
サールナイン密林に行く
船が出ておる
It's an animal paradise.
そこは動物だけのパラダイスじゃ
No one comes near it.
人は寄りつかん
There, you can train to
your heart's content.
思う存分 力を獲得できるぞ
A ship...
船… ノッカーが来たら大変だ
A ship would be dangerous
if the Nokkers came.
It's not that much to endure!
少しの我慢じゃ！
You're going to be trapped forever
if you don't stop worrying.
んなこと気にしとったら
いつまでたっても身動きできん
All right.
分かった
Let's go.
行こう
Here we are!
（ピオラン）あったぞ この船じゃ
This is the ship.
Ma'am, this ship is full.
（トナリ）お客さま！
この船は満員ですので
向こうの船へ案内いたします
Allow me to show you
to that ship over there.
This way, please.
こちらへどうぞ
ロバは お預かりします
I'll take care of your donkey.
Thanks.
（ピオラン）ご苦労さん
ふあ～ 休も休も
Time for a break.
Women with me, please.
女性は こちらへ お願いします
Is that a rule?
へ？　そんなルールがあるのか？
This area is dangerous.
この辺 物騒ですので…
すみません
I'm sorry.
Well then, Fushi, I'll see you there.
（ピオラン）そんじゃ フシ
着いたらな
Yeah.
うん
Come, you're with me.
（ウーロイ）
さあ お前は こっちだ！
Over here.
（ウーロイ）こっち！
（フシ）え…
Get in.
（ウーロイ）入れ！
（フシ）ハッ
（男）おい 待てよ 待ちやがれ
（男）出せっつってんだよ
I'm going to hand out your tickets.
（船長）今から切符を渡す
（男たちの怒号）
Each of you, put your hand out.
１人ずつ手を出せ！
（男たちの悲鳴）
Next!
（船員）次 お前！
（フシ）うおっ
You!
うっ くあっ…
Next!
ハッ
（船長）次！
（男）うう… ギャー
Next!
（フシ）ハァ ハァ…
（船長）次！
（男）助けてくれ
（男）離せ！
ハッ ピオラン！
（男）出してくれ！
Pioran!
Welcome, prisoners!
ようこそ 囚人ども
Starting today, you're all family!
今日から お前らはファミリーだ
You're all headed for the one place in
the world that'll accept trash like you.
今から向かうのは
お前らクズどもを
世界で唯一 受け入れてくれる⸺
ありがたい場所だ
There is where your last life begins.
そこで お前らの
最後の人生が始まる
Welcome to heaven...
あの世の楽園
ジャナンダ島(とう)へ ようこそ！
Jananda Island!
What is going on?
（フシ）何が どうなってるんだ？
Where's Pioran?
ピオランは どこ？
You, hold it.
（班長）何だ お前
足かせがねえじゃねえか
Where are your shackles?
Your brand is missing, too.
（フシ）え？
（班長）焼き印もねえ
That's odd...
まさか…
Did you get on with the prisoners by mistake?
シャバの お方が
間違えて乗ったのか？
I'm sorry, boss!
（トナリ）ごめんなさい 班長！
（班長）ん？
I made a mistake.
（トナリ）あたしのミスです！
I see.
Be careful from now on.
（班長）そうか
今度から気つけろよ
Trust is important to our business.
こういうのは信用が大事だからな
All right.
I'll take him back.
（トナリ）
はい！　お送りしておきます
This way.
（トナリ）こっち こっち
（フシ）うわ…
Where's Pioran?
ピオランは どこ？
オレと一緒にいた人
The woman who was with me?
Dunno.
さあ… きっと
もう収容されてると思うよ
She's probably been taken in already.
Don't worry.
（フシ）え？
（トナリ）安心して
Everyone who comes here
learns to smile eventually.
ここへ来る人は みんな
次第に笑顔になっていくんだ
I wonder why, though.
でも それって
どっちの意味だろ？
Is it because they're happy here?
楽しいから？
Or because if they don't act happy,
they'll lose their minds?
それとも楽しく振る舞わないと
やっていけないから？
Wait!
あ… ちょっと！
Don't just wander off!
勝手に どっか行かないでよ！
Huh?
あれ？
ん… めんどくっさ！
What a pain.
Over there.
（フシ）むこうダ…
Where's the entrance?
（フシ）
入り口どこ？　見つからない
I can't find it.
I can't dig down.
下… 掘れない
（フシ）えいっ
Can I make my way up this way?
（フシ）
これで何とか上まで行けるか？
（フシ）ぐっ
んっ
うっ
（強い風が吹く音）
あっ！
（地面に落ちる音）
うっ
（サンデル）ギャッ
（ウーロイ･トナリ）うえっ
I'm not looking!
（ミァ）見ない！
Hello...
こん… ちわあ
ハッ
Did you... see that?
今の… 見た？
I did!
見ました！
That was awesome!
すごかったです！
Oh, should we keep it a secret?
あっ 秘密にしときます？
Hand me that bow.
その弓… 貸して
え？　はい
Here.
Huh? How do you use these things again?
（フシ）あれ… どうやるんだっけ
Right, like this.
あっ こうだ！
I can make it over there if I have that bird.
（フシ）あの鳥を手に入れれば
向こうへ行ける
I don't have a choice.
やるしかない
Okay.
よし
Not "okay"!
（フシ）だっ…
（ミァ）“よし”じゃねえ！
ッテ… な… 何するんだ！
Wh-What was that for?!
This is my partner.
こいつは私の相棒だよ
You can't do that.
ダメだよ そんなことしちゃ
Give me back my bow.
おい 弓返せ
H-Hey! Hang on!
お… おい 待てよ！
People like you get played with
like toys when they're alone!
お前みたいなのが１人でいると
オモチャにされちゃうぞ
I'll wait, so tell me...
待つから教えて
How do I get up there?
あそこに行くには
どうすればいい？
I dunno.
さあ 知らない
Me, neither.
Nor I.
（ウーロイ）俺も
（サンデル）同じく
You're looking for your
buddy Pioran, right?
ピオランとかいう
連れを捜してるんだね
That's unfortunate.
だったら残念だったね
Even if you find her,
she won't be getting out.
会えたとしても
彼女は外には出られないよ
（フシ）え？
Violent, irredeemable
murderers are brought
（トナリ）この島は
いろんな土地から 手に負えない
凶悪殺人犯を集めてるんだ
from all over the place to
be kept on this island.
It's a prison island.
いわば監獄島さ
Once you're a prisoner here,
there's no getting out.
一度ここに囚人として入ったら
もう二度と
外へは出ていけないんだよ
Remember when they branded your hand?
手に焼き印を入れられただろ？
That marks you as a prisoner.
あれが囚人の印(しるし)さ
So long as she has that brand,
she's a prisoner here.
あの印が あるかぎり
彼女は ここの住人なのさ
Prisoner?! You were the one
who brought us here!
囚人って
お前が連れてきたんだろ！
My bad!
ごめんごめん！
間違えちゃったの ホントホント
It was a mistake, I swear.
Don't bullshit me.
とぼけるな！　そんなわけあるか
That was no mistake!
Let me make it up to you, then.
じゃあ おわびをさせてくれ
I'll tell you the one realistic
way to grant your wish.
君の望みをかなえる 現実的で
唯一の方法を教えてあげるよ
This is it!
これさ！
You have to win in this arena.
君が この闘技場で優勝することさ
♪～
～♪
Preview
Jananda, island of the lawless.
（観察者）無法の島 ジャナンダ島
An island where prisoners kill each
other to have their wishes granted.
囚人が望みをかなえるために
殺し合う島
Fushi, being immortal, came to
be the hope of five children.
不死身のフシは
５人の子供たちの希望となった
Fushi has yet to notice the footsteps
approaching from the past.
過去から忍び寄る足音に
フシは まだ気づかない
Jananda, Island of Freedom